Finding Aid for the Barbara and Willard Morgan photographs and papers LSC.2278
UCLA Library Special Collections
Barbara and Willard Morgan photographs and papers
1850s-2008
1919-1985
UCLA Library Special Collections
Morgan, Barbara Brooks, 1900-1992
Morgan, Willard D. (Willard Detering), 1900-1967
LSC.2278
478.8 linear feet (616 boxes)
2 audiovisual carriers (1 unprocessed film reel, 1 unprocessed videocassette)
2 born-digital carriers (2 unprocessed optical discs)
25.8 linear feet (23 unprocessed boxes)
53.4 Gigabytes (22,675 unprocessed files)
The Barbara and Willard Morgan photographs and papers relate to the personal lives and professional careers of artists and photographers Barbara Brooks Morgan (1900-1992) and Willard Detering Morgan (1900-1967). The collection includes correspondence; writings; publications; professional papers; exhibition materials; and individual and collaborative project materials. Visual materials comprise a significant portion of the collection: Barbara and Willard Morgan's photographic archives, as well as Barbara's drawings, paintings, and prints. The collection reflects the Morgans' close associations with photographers, dancers, architects, and other artists, including Martha Graham, Ansel Adams, and Richard Neutra. Family letters, documents, photographs, and ephemera, as well as business materials related to the family publishing business, are also included.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL, AUDIO, AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed digital, audio, and audiovisual materials. For information about the access status of the material that you are looking for, refer to the Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital, audio, and audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase/Gift from the Morgan family, 2014. Additional gifts from the Morgan family, 2016, 2017, 2018, and 2019.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9977219453606533
Custodial History
Following the passing of Willard Morgan, then Barbara Morgan, multiple Morgan family members maintained the materials and managed the archives for many years.
Administrative/Biographical History
Barbara Brooks Morgan was born in 1900 in Buffalo, Kansas, and Willard Detering Morgan was born in 1900 in Snohomish, Washington. Their families later relocated to Southern California, and they met while students at Pomona High School. Willard attended Pomona College, and later earned a living writing articles and illustrating them with his own photographs. Barbara attended UCLA from 1919 to 1923 and joined the art faculty there in 1925, where she taught Design, Landscape and Woodcut. Willard continued to photograph around the Los Angeles area, inspired by the architectural work of his friend Richard Neutra, as well as quintessentially local structures such as drive-in markets. The Morgans married in 1925, and spent their summers traveling the Southwest with painting and photography equipment, experiences that were deeply affecting for both. On these trips the Morgans experimented with 35mm Leica cameras, novel at the time for their small size.
In 1930, when Willard Morgan received a job offer from E. Leitz, Inc., the manufacturer of Leica cameras, the couple moved to New York City. Barbara put painting aside at that time to focus primarily on photography, a decision that coincided with the birth of the couple's two children, Douglas in 1932 and Lloyd in 1935. While Willard worked for Leica and moved on to other photography-related jobs with the Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), Life magazine, and Look magazine, Barbara achieved recognition photographing modern dancers and experimenting with photomontage. While a student at UCLA, she was guided by Arthur Wesley Dow's principles of art synthesis, and the Chinese Six Canons of Painting, whose principles of "rhythmic vitality" or the essence of life force directed her artistic expression. Working as a photographer allowed her to partner light energy with the physical and spiritual energies in dance. Her photographs from the 1938 Bennington College Festival of Modern Dance, and a book project, Martha Graham: Sixteen Dances in Photographs, cemented her reputation as a significant contemporary photographer. She was invited to exhibit and teach at Black Mountain College in 1943, mounted a solo exhibition at MoMA in 1945, and, with a consortium of other photographers, founded Aperture magazine in 1952. Over the years her interests also included children's growth, which resulted in photography projects with camps, schools, and colleges, and culminated in her book Summer's Children.
Meanwhile, Willard had started a publishing business which focused primarily on photography books and manuals. The company published a variety of how-to books and technical manuals, including The Leica Manual and early editions of Ansel Adams' Zone System book series. Willard also edited The Complete Photographer, the ten-volume Encyclopedia of Photography published by the National Educational Alliance, and also maintained a typography collection and working print shop in the basement of the family's Scarsdale home. Willard Morgan died in 1967.
Barbara Morgan continued to make photographs, as well as lecture, write, and teach on photography in the decades following Willard's death. In the 1970s, she was invited to participate in a number of workshops, including with Ansel Adams in Yosemite, and also mounted a second solo show at MoMA. Her photography continues to be exhibited widely, and her life and work is the subject of numerous articles and interviews. Barbara Morgan died in 1992.
Scope and Content
Collection is comprised of materials related to the personal and professional lives of Barbara Brooks Morgan and Willard Detering Morgan. Collection includes correspondence, writings, exhibition materials, and professional papers, as well as photographic prints, slides, and negatives related to the photography careers of Barbara Morgan and Willard Morgan. Materials reflect the Morgans' personal and professional associations with photographers, dancers, architects, and other artists, including Ansel Adams, Martha Graham, and Richard Neutra.
Barbara Morgan materials include personal and professional correspondence; professional papers related to the management of her photography career; materials related to book projects, including Martha Graham: Sixteen Dances in Photographs, and Summer's Children; articles, lectures, and teaching materials; personal journals; biographical articles; and subject files. Photographic material consists of negatives, slides, and prints covering the majority of her professional output, including original negatives and exhibition quality prints featuring modern dancers such as Martha Graham and José Limón; nature; children, and her experimental photomontage and photograms. Barbara Morgan's drawings, paintings, and prints are also in the collection.
Willard Morgan materials include correspondence and papers related to his positions with E. Leitz Inc., MoMA, and Life magazine, as well as his writing and editing career; personal journals; biographical materials; working files; and correspondence and documents related to his longtime interest in printing and typography. Photographic material includes negatives, slides, and prints primarily related to the architecture of Southern California, including the work of Richard Neutra.
There is also material related to the early collaborative work of Barbara and Willard, including journals and images of their trips through the American Southwest in the late 1920s, documentation of the Barnes Foundation collections, and photographs of their early days in New York City. Due to the collaborative nature of this work, authorship of the photographic material is sometimes ambiguous. Also in the collection is Morgan family materials, such as correspondence (including early courtship letters between Barbara and Willard), genealogy documents, and photographs. Additionally, the collection contains correspondence, book proofs, and other materials related to the family publishing business.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Barbara Morgan exhibition materials
Series 2: Barbara Morgan correspondence
Series 3: Barbara Morgan professional materials
Series 4: Barbara Morgan photographic projects
Series 5: Barbara Morgan writings
Series 6: Barbara Morgan UCLA student and teaching career
Series 7: Barbara Morgan professional activities
Series 8: Barbara Morgan personal and biographical materials
Series 9: Barbara Morgan photographic material
Series 10: Barbara Morgan drawings, paintings, and prints
Series 11: Barbara Morgan subject files
Series 12: Willard Morgan photography career
Series 13: Willard Morgan writings and published materials
Series 14: Willard Morgan architectural photography and projects
Series 15: Willard Morgan typography files
Series 16: Willard Morgan personal and biographical materials
Series 17: Willard Morgan working files
Series 18: Collaborative work
Series 19: Family materials
Series 20: Publishing company materials
Series 21: Artifacts and audiovisual materials
Separated Materials
Twenty-six boxes of nitrate negatives were removed from the collection and housed in two flammable safety cabinets. Nitrate negatives must be digitized in order to be available for access. Please contact Special Collections reference (AskLSC@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
Additionally, 8 boxes of acetate negatives, prints, and contact sheets were separated for treatment by UCLA Library Preservation Studios.
Related Material
Collection about Barbara Morgan (Collection 1112). Available at Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Barbara Morgan Wight Gallery collection (Collection 1872). Available at Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Barbara Morgan photographs (Collection 1873). Available at Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Photographers -- United States -- Archives.; Women photographers -- Archives.; Morgan, Willard D. (Willard Detering), 1900-1967 -- Archives; Morgan, Barbara Brooks, 1900-1992 -- Archives
- Series 1: Barbara Morgan exhibition materials, 1923-2006
  Administrative/Biographical History
  While best known for her dance photography, Barbara Morgan produced and exhibited a wide range of artistic works. Exhibitions showcased Morgan's drawings, gouache, lithographs, oil paintings, sculpture, watercolors, and woodcuts, light drawings, photograms, and photomontage, in addition to her other photographs.
  Morgan's work has been featured in solo and group shows all over the world, including national and international traveling exhibitions. In the United States, notable institutions that organized exhibitions include George Eastman House and the International Museum of Photography, MoMA, and the Smithsonian Institution's National Gallery of Art, National Museum of History and Technology, and National Portrait Gallery. Morgan's work has also been exhibited internationally, in Germany, France, Japan, Sweden, Italy, and Egypt.
  Morgan's solo exhibitions were among her most significant showings. One of her early major photography exhibits, Modern American Dance, was organized by the Smithsonian's National Gallery of Art in the mid-1940s. This show traveled in both the United States and internationally, visiting Cuba and parts of South America, where the exhibit was known as La Danza Moderna. After gaining notoriety as a photographer, Morgan eventually returned to some of her earlier creative methods. Her 1961 exhibit at the Ruth Sherman Gallery was one of her first major drawing and painting exhibits during this period of her life. A major retrospective exhibit of Morgan's photography was installed at MoMA in 1972.
  Scope and Content
  This series relates to exhibitions of Barbara Morgan's works of art between the 1920s and mid-2000s. Materials include correspondence, publicity documents (such as fliers, press releases, and reception invitations), checklists and catalogs, loan agreements, reviews, notes, receipts, and congratulatory letters. Some of these materials document lectures and seminars Morgan gave in conjunction with her exhibitions.
  Several folders also contain photographic prints, panoramic photographs, slides, and negatives of Morgan's exhibition installations. Exhibitions with extensive photographic documentation include her 1934 painting exhibition at the Mellon Galleries, 1969-1970 show at the National Museum of History and Technology, and 1977 photography exhibition at Marquette University.
  Morgan's exhibitions with less documentation are arranged by decade at the end of the series, followed by other exhibition-related materials, including exhibition requests and correspondence, lists, notes, and other photographic documentation. The exhibition lists are rough lists, created by Morgan, of her exhibitions between 1925 and 1986. Collector lists are of individuals or organizations that own Morgan's works. The numbered list of works of art (Box 218, folder 14) contains the names and serial numbers of her drawings, paintings, and prints created between 1920 and 1967. The numbers correspond to those written in pencil on the verso of most of the pieces in Series 10: Barbara Morgan's drawings, paintings, and prints. The photographic documentation of her works of art are images that have not been attributed to a specific exhibition. Exhibition notes are planning-related.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED DIGITAL MATERIALS: Digital materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email AskLSC@library.ucla.edu.
  - 4th Weltausstellung der Photographie, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - VII Photographers Gallery, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 92nd Street Y, Dance and the People, The Passion of Barbara Morgan, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Also includes correspondence, reviews, and Dance and the People "The Passion of Barbara Morgan" article on photography exhibition by Barbara Morgan at the 92nd Street Y, May 11-July 13 1994.
  - 92nd Street Young Men's and Young Women's Hebrew Association, Famous Faces at the Y: 1934-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 253 Gallery of Photographic Art, Visions and Vistas, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Akron Art Museum, A History of Women Photographers, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Craftmen's Council, Visual Communication in the Crafts, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Repertory Dance Company, Gestures of Life: Martha Graham's Legacy through the Lens of Barbara Morgan, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Amon Carter Museum of Western Art, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folders 8-11)
  - Amon Carter Museum of Western Art, Masterworks from the Photography Collection, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Aperture Foundation, Aperture at 50: A Celebration of Photography, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Arizona State University, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folders 14-15)
  - Baldwin Street Gallery of Photography, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folders 16-17)
  - Barnard College, American Modern Dance: 1935-1945, Highlights of Dance Productions by Martha Graham, Doris Humphrey and Charles Weidman, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bennington College, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bennington Festival of the Modern Dance, 1938-1944 (Box 2, Folders 1-2)
    Photographs from the festival were used to create a traveling catalog of Morgan's work that circulated through four rounds of tours between 1939 and 1942.
  - Boston Women's Collective, Women: A Photographic Exhibition, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Briarcliff Public Library, Barbara Morgan: Photographs and Drawings, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Brooklyn Museum, Designs and Costumes for the Dance, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bruce Museum, Images of Dance, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bruce Silverstein Gallery, Barbara Morgan: Leaps and Bounds, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bruce Silverstein Gallery, Invisible Urges: Prints, Drawings, Watercolors, & Photographs, 1921-1980, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bushnell Center for the Performing Arts, In the American Grain: Barbara Morgan Photographs, 1935-1944, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes one 3 1/2 inch floppy disk labeled "In the American Grain: Barbara Morgan Photographs 1935-1944." Label indicates the disk contains a price sheet and curator's text.
  - Camera Obscura Gallery, Barbara Morgan: Retrospective, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Carnegie Institute of Technology, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ceeje Galleries, Barbara Morgan: Paintings, Photographs, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Chateauvallon Dance Festival, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Chrysler Museum of Art, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Chrysler Museum of Art, Martha Graham Dance Photographs by Barbara Morgan, 2005 (Box 2, Folders 15-16)
  - Columbia University, A Portfolio of the Dance, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Columbus Museum, An American Century of Photography: From Dry-Plate to Digital, circa 2001 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Connecticut College Dance Festival, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Daniel Wolf Incorporated, Barbara Morgan: Limited Editions, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Danziger Gallery, Barbara Morgan: A Retrospective, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Daytona Beach Community College, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Detroit Jewish Community Center, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Detroit Public Library, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Doris Humphrey Repertory Dance Company, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Douglas Elliott Gallery, Barbara Morgan: 55 Year Retrospective, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Equivalents Gallery, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Erie Art Museum, Light on the Feet: Masters of Dance Photography, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Exchange National Bank of Chicago, 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Five College Dance Department, Riffing on a Tradition: Pearl Primus and Jawole Willa Jo Zollar, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Floating Foundation of Photography, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Focus Gallery, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Fotografiska Museet, Tusen och en bild, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Franklin Institute Science Museum, Lensless Photography, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Friends of Photography, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Galerie Zabriskie, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Gallery 292, Barbara Morgan: Visual Metaphor, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - George Eastman House, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - George Eastman House, The Invisible World Revealed, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - George Eastman House, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Harvey School for Boys, Barbara Morgan: Drawings and Watercolors, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Hastings Creative Arts Council, Barbara Morgan: Photographs and Paintings, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Hoff-Barthelson Music School, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Holden Luntz Gallery, All that Jazz, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hollis Taggart Galleries, Important Modernist Works on Paper, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Hollis Taggart Galleries, Concerning Expressionism, 1998 (Box 153, Folder 2)
  - Howard Greenberg Gallery, Dance in America, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Hudson River Museum, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Hudson River Museum, Light and Lens, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Hudson River Museum, Women in America: The Second Hundred Years, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Hudson River Museum, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Infinite Eye Gallery, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Institute of American Indian Arts, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - International Center of Photography, Remarkable American Women, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - International Center of Photography, Recollections: Ten Women of Photography, 1977-1983; 1990 (Box 4, Folders 3-7, Box 153, Folder 2)
    Box 4, folder 7 also includes one 8 x 10 print by Kitty Reeve of five of the women photographers, including Barbara Morgan.
  - International Museum of Photography at George Eastman House, Barbara Morgan: Photomontage, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folders 8-10)
  - Iona College, Barbara Morgan 1935-1945: Dialogues with Dance, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Jacob Burns Film Center, Martha Graham: Photographs by Barbara Morgan, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Jane Corkin Gallery, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Jeffrey Fuller Fine Art, Barbara Morgan: Photographs, Paintings, Drawings, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - J. Hunt Galleries, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Johns Hopkins Hospital, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Karen Horney Clinic, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Kathleen Ewing Gallery, Barbara Morgan: Martha Graham, Sixteen Dances in Photographs, and Photomontage, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Katonah Gallery, 1960-1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Kingpitcher Gallery for Contemporary Art, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Larchmont Public Library, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Laurence Miller Gallery, Barbara Morgan: The Spirit of New York 1930-1945, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - MacDowell Colony, Seven Decades at the Colony, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Marquette University, 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folders 6-9)
  - Marquette University, Barbara Morgan: Prints, Drawings, Watercolors and Photography, 1982-1990, 1996 (Box 5, Folders 10-12, Box 153, Folder 3, Box 215)
  - Marquette University, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Marquette University, Faces of Modern Dance: Barbara Morgan Photographs, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 14, Box 153, Folders 4-7)
    Material related to the exhibition and accompanying catalog of the same name. For the photographic prints exhibited in the Marquette University exhibit, as well as works included in earlier versions of the exhibition checklist, see Series 9: Barbara Morgan photographic material, Subseries 9.2: Dance photography.
  - Martha Graham Center of Contemporary Dance, 50th Anniversary Celebration, 1975 (Box 5, Folders 15-16)
  - Marymount College, Tarrytown, Shadows, Light, Movement: Moments in American History, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Light 7, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Being Without Clothes, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Eye of the West: Camera Vision and Cultural Consensus, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Mellon Galleries, 1934 (Box 5, Folders 21-22)
  - Mellon Galleries, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Middle Tennessee State University, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - At Mono Lake, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Montclair Art Museum, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folders 4-5)
    Includes acetate negatives
  - Museum of Fine Arts, St. Petersburg, FL, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Museum of Fine Arts, St. Petersburg, FL, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - MoMA, In and Out of Focus, 1948-1950 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - MoMA, Family of Man, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folders 9-10)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folders 11-14)
  - Neikrug Galleries, Why Photography?, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Neuberger Museum of Art, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Neue Gesellschaft fur bildende Kunst, Frauen in der Kunst, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - New Canaan Library, Drawings: Barbara Morgan, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - New York Public Library, 1939; 1997 (Box 7, Folder 5, Box 549)
    box 549 contains 5 x 7 exhibition negatives.
  - Ohio Silver Gallery, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Orange County Art Association, Super Cream, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Ovo Photo, Femmes Photographes, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 8)